all right welcome back
uh yeah I yesterday we had a wonderful
ceremony you know they asked me to go to
the ceremony I'm like I don't want to go
to the ceremony and they're like please
and I'm like oh can I just go for one
minute and they're like
okay and then uh I went to the ceremony
and it was so much fun I stayed and I
had a good time which is unusual
so uh
we uh opened the we we consecrated the
first stuper
yesterday and we have some photos for
you guys
[Applause]
online uh people read the whole good
name I think good name's prayers a
prayers
H this was a little piece of stuper that
everybody
[Applause]
got
[Music]
yay
and uh thank you to all the sponsors and
we had you know the two main people uh
which is venerable cinam and Hanley were
there yesterday who worked for years uh
to get the stupas done they are pure
marble uh which is very very difficult
very very expensive the marble was
fashioned in Portugal with lasers and
only the Portuguese know how to do do
that marble
right and uh so we they finished the
first one and we consecrated it
yesterday we got six more to go or seven
six more and uh one SP the the the
biggest sponsor who everybody knows Dr W
uh has asked me and the board if we
could make uh the final
stoa we we'd like to make the final
stupa up above
uh we'd like to make it about double
height or double height I can say yeah
three times higher and uh it'll have a a
special room inside where you can
meditate uh we think about I think seven
to 10 people can meditate in on inside
the stupa so that's this grand plan we
have and uh so we'd like to thank
everyone it's been a big expans
sometimes I'm a little bit doubt that we
should spend so much money uh but these
things last for centuries and I think
all of us have visited great stupas in
Indonesia or China India and they last
way way beyond our our life and they
inspire people for many generations and
I think there will be blessings in these
stupas not just to have a place of you
know where people worship but where
people learn the teachings also and so
that's the goal of these stupas that
should last for thousands of years but
also the the teachings connected with
the stupas should last so that's the
goal and it was very very beautiful
yesterday thank you all the sponsors for
this and thank you the the hard work of
the diamond mountain uh stuff stuff
especially cinnamon hle they they they
had endless headaches endless headaches
the mine behind diamond mountain where
the marble is taken out of it hasn't
been active for a hundred years and they
they really opened it back up and it's
kind of a big blessing because that
marble extends into diamond mountain uh
it goes about 2,000 ft deep so it's cool
all right let's get to
work you guys
ready me and Francisco every morning
were like you got the same one that I
do yeah that's good okay
uh this is about the prayers of good
name who stuper we opened
yesterday uh
he made prayers he made eight prayers
and uh for people in the future and he
prayed that uh he could uh that people's
poverty or problems with your finances
let's put it that way uh that he made a
prayer that if you say his name at least
seven times a day or something then uh
you would be released from
poverty and we started talking about it
yesterday yesterday and
uh we mentioned a book by dharmakirti
pranava the the roote text on accurate
perception and uh in that book uh they
claim that the Buddhists have reach the
Perfection of other people's goals and
their own goals and then there's a
bitter debate in the monastery uh you
know I I understand that the Buddha
maybe has reached their own goals
but I don't see how you can say that
they have perfected other people's goals
because we can see there's lots of poor
people left in the world how can you say
the Buddha is
perfect uh if there's still poor people
in the world I mean how can you say
their work is how can you say they are
final Buddha if there's still poor
people in the world you know and that's
a huge debate uh and we could debate it
and I mean we debate it for a month in
the monastery
like many many hours but the bottom line
is uh they do destroy poverty because
they destroy the misunderstanding which
creates poverty okay and that's a very
uh it's a sign of our own
misunderstanding you know you say do do
I have the first
link of The Wheel of Life we talked
about it in words class I think uh do I
have the the do I possess the first link
of the 12 Links of the suffering Wheel
of Life and there's a test you can do
self test like a self covid test or
something and uh you could do a test on
yourself and and it is how willing are
you to give how willing are you to give
what away what you have you know are you
willing to give away what you have and
me you know Rob russer and his S no they
I called them before I came to diam
Mountain I said I'm going to diamond
mountain and they're like yeah we
know CU we take money out of the company
we take money out of our company and we
you know we donate it so I and we try to
there's a bad word in English can I say
it no my wife doesn't
like is there a better way to say that
it's like when you take a needle and you
poke somebody in the butt and they they
like wake them up you know so I I I need
the needle to poke the donations in the
butt and uh that's the money that I
bring here uh so I'm like do we have any
extra money in the company can we can we
kind of what do you call it blackmail
people to donate you know and and then
uh I get to a point uh where they say
yeah you can do that but it's going to
be a hard year next year you know you
don't you won't have any money next year
or you know the company will be short on
money next year and then the qu if you
want to check your own level of
misunderstanding okay do you want to
check if you have link number one in
your heart or not it's how much do you
hesitate
uh when it comes you know it's easy to
donate your extra money and then it
comes down to your real money and then
you're like I don't know you know and
that's a sign of Link number one okay if
you want to know if you have link number
one because that
hesitation believes that if you give the
last amount you won't have anything and
that's total ignorance that's total
ignorance okay if you don't give the
last
amount that's that's when you start
having financial problems you know what
I mean when you hesitate you are
hesitating to give in my case and I I
also hesitate you know I give away the I
sure that we have but when you get down
to the company company money I'm like I
don't know you know and uh if that's a
sign that you have link number one in
your heart okay that that hesitation
because you believe you won't get it
back or you don't believe you're going
to get 10 times more okay so that's a
sign that you don't understand the
Dharma
okay if you had perfected giving right
sharing uh you give everything because
because you know you're just going to
get more you see when you hesitate you
get back less when you don't hesitate
you get back more okay by the way if you
don't hesitate and give and then
hesitate later that's a
disaster okay all right that cancels the
whole that cancels the whole positive
sansara you know like okay I'll say it
again if you decide to
give tell it hurts right because you
understand this is how to make
money but then you you doubt three days
later you're like man gish's so
persuasive
and I gave all my last money and oh
stupid you know when you doubt at the
end uh then you you hurt the karma okay
so if you're not ready don't do it okay
uh but if you but if you understand it
then do it and don't doubt it okay and
and it will it'll come back more and I'm
just saying I'm not trying to get money
out of you I'm trying to talk to gessi
Michael a lot of my teaching is for
gashi Michael he needs it uh so I I'm
like don't forget where your money comes
from come on you can do it you know and
if I had a lot of sleep I believe him
and if I didn't have a lot of sleep I
don't believe
him so stupid right anyway has the
Buddha overcome poverty yes is does the
world still have poor people yes yes
okay not no contradiction no
contradiction what do they see the
world we don't know probably they don't
see poor people and then there's another
question that comes from that and I'm
going to talk about it later okay all
[Music]
right next slide Francisco you're having
a good day
uh
okay and thank you again all your Tech
guys uh you got don't get to see them I
get to see them all day and it's really
beautiful it's like uh the eight
medicine Buddhist or something you know
I get to look at them uh all during the
class and they're cool people and
they're very generous with their time
and uh we should give them a
[Applause]
hand
and some of them have been doing it for
a long long time Gina's been designing
our our books and and our all of our
prayer books and stuff for many years
and thank you for that
[Applause]
yeah please live long
life okay um here's the question from
the okay and we're still we had when we
started the program we had six chapters
left and Grandpa foolishly thought he's
going to finish six chapters and uh
we're gonna finish two chapters and then
I'm sorry we have to keep going in the
other
program uh so we're covering uh this
chapter what is it in last chapter was
an investigation of
tatag the ones gas and this one is an
investigation
of uh negative emotions okay we're still
in that chapter okay chapter
24 then uh we still have 25 26 27 to do
okay so we're in
24 say
did oh I'm sorry he Mis wrote it here I
think we hang on one
second I think we're in 24 now I'm
sorry
what is
24 Tru yeah I'm sorry yeah we're in 24
which is investigation of the four
higher truth and now he says if neither
the Dharma nor the community exist then
how can the Buddha exist if you talk
about emptiness the way you are then you
are hurting the whole the whole idea of
the three jewels okay so I'd like to
talk about the three jewels and you know
I went to my teacher uh straight from
Princeton
and I went directly on graduation the
day after graduation I went to my
teacher and uh my professor handed me
over to my llama and said take good care
of him you know and uh he drove me there
uh so anyway
uh I
was I came out of a Christian background
I was living at the university the last
year of the University I didn't have any
money at all I didn't have enough money
to stay in the
dormatory uh so I had to find a room
somewhere and I stayed in the Christian
church in the in the Christ so I was
friends with the with the priest you
know they in so they let me in the my
religion was Episcopal and the priest
can marry and they had kids and so I was
a babysitter for the for the priest's
kids you know and I they gave me a room
in the church and then uh so I one day
I'm in the Christian church sleeping
there and then the next day I'm at this
Buddhist temple comic
Mongolians and there's a lot of
differences there were a lot of
differences and one of them was the
Trinity okay in in my where I grew up in
Christian religion uh they say God has
three
parts they say father Son and Holy Ghost
okay so father is like
this invisible big guy somewhere and son
is Jesus Christ and then Holy Ghost is I
don't know it's like the spirit of the
whole thing you know and uh so I grew up
with these three dudes you know and TR
Som and uh I I'm comfortable with this
idea you know I grew up with that since
I was a little kid and and then I come
to the next day I'm in the comic
Mongolian Tempo and and my teacher's
like it's three okay it's three guys I'm
like good you know I can understand that
you know and he said Buddha Dharma okay
and I'm like great that fits yeah you
know and uh and then slowly I realized
they're not the same at all okay slowly
I
understand uh what's the three jewels
right and and but I want to
say I think a lot of Buddhists uh think
that the three jewels are like the the
Trinity or the three parts of
Christianity I think a lot of Buddhists
think that the three jewels are three
guys somewhere and you have to be nice
to them or they won't be good to you
because that's kind of what we learned
in the Christian church by the way which
I don't think is the essence of
Christianity I think real Christians are
are practicing much deeper but there's a
common idea that there's three guys and
then in Buddhism I think there's a
common idea that there's three guys you
know and you have to be nice to them or
something like that and then uh in the
in the gashi course one of the earliest
uh topics Aban Cara which is what Tim is
translating uh one of the ear and by the
way we spend 12 years on it the first 12
years of the gishi course half the gishi
course is one small book and that's the
one that Tim is translating and they
they talk about uh the three jewels who
is the three jewels okay and what does
it mean in Buddhism when you take refuge
say I go for
[Music]
Refuge
this is ancient going for refuge in
Sanskrit or P these are you know I go
for Refuge so what does it mean to go
for Refuge to the three jewels who are
the three jewels uh and I I loveed that
topic I was blown away I was so amazed
when I read the in the gashi course when
we studied the three guys I'm like wow
that's completely different you know
from what I was thinking you know and I
was so impressed I made it ACI course
number two two or three two two yeah and
and I'll summarize it for you here
because it it comes in N okay n is
talking about it okay and he says here's
this is half the verses in his most
famous book are the other guy talking
okay half the verses in wisdom are
criticism from the other guy okay uh and
sometimes it's hard to tell who's
talking you're like that sounds great
and then you then the commentary says
this is the stupid guy and and you're
like oh yeah I knew that so uh he says
if the Dharma so it's the other guy
talking okay this is a
Tar this is a
pranga this is a
sarcasm from the other guy uh oh so
dharma's empty yes Sana is empty yes
okay then they don't exist then how's
there a Buddha you know that's the other
guy talking okay it's called a statement
of consequence
pranga it it means if you tell me a
wrong thing
like no like the Dharma has no nature of
its
own and the s or the community has no
nature of its own then I say well okay
then there's no
Buddha okay that's a sarcastic response
okay if you don't know about it uh get
married your wife will say oh so that
means you know
we do anyway uh
so this is the other guy talking okay if
there's no
Dharma as and if there's no s then I
guess there's no Buddha I'll give a $100
if you can tell
me what he's thinking and it's not
obvious you have to think about
it hundred bucks I'll say it again he
says if there's if the first two Jewels
don't exist okay well sorry if Jewel
number two and Jewel number three don't
exist if there's no Dharma and there's
no community no s then how can there be
a Buddha he said that why is he thinking
like
that what's the relationship between
Buddha and the Dharma and
the um I don't don't say what you're
thinking think no think deeper think
deeper um I think that this guy is
thinking that nothing is
real but um it is a consequence of
misunderstanding MH uh and therefore he
thinks that nothing exists at all which
is wrong because um there is Dharma
there is s and there is
Buddha uh it's a good guess and it's not
the right one okay and I I'll say it
again he says his pranga his statement
of consequence he's like if there's no
Dharma and there's no Community then how
can there be a
Buddha that's his
statement I think this is one of the
extremes of the I mid way say again nism
this this is going into the nalism side
it's going I'm sorry what you call it
nihilism oh nihilism okay yeah okay oh
yeah that's okay but but what I'm saying
is if you're GNA give me a correct
answer I'll give you a clue he's saying
there's a
relationship between the Buddha and the
Dharma and the sa and if these don't
exist then this one can't exist what's
it mean if there's no understanding of
emptiness and there's no one who seen
emptiness directly then there can't
be
uh yeah that's okay I'll buy it okay
okay but I'll say it a little
differently okay if I was in my
Christian days right if I was in my
Christian days and by the way I I deeply
follow both I I think they're very
beautiful I learned many good things in
the church and I love them and I keep
them but uh in in that Trinity in that
gang of three guys
uh in that model Buddha made the Dharma
and sa you see what I mean uh Buddha
designed the Dharma and sa okay so if
Dharma and sa don't exist
then what's the purpose of a Buddha that
there's no no need for Buddha if there's
no
Community uh and if there's no
realizations or teachings then why you
need a Buddha and the g of disagrees
with me the G says don't think like that
don't think like the Christian three
it's not like that he wants to flip it
around the garer wants to flip
what's
that if there's
no D sa how do you create a Buddha you
see what I mean when you grow up in the
in the Christian church uh the the model
would be Buddha worked hard and made a
teaching and because of the teaching a
community exists okay and the guardian
says don't think like that
Dharma
came Community came and they created
Buddhist you know it's very interesting
that's what you said right
[Applause]
[Music]
Rebecca she's
like okay so yeah when he says here if
there's no Dharma and there's no
Community then how can you have a Buddha
it means the
next you see what I mean if there's no
teaching and there's no people that
follow the teaching how could you have a
Buddha now who's talking who's asking
the
question the other guy the other guy
he's attacking us he's attacking us you
said there's no Dharma you said there's
no Sana so how do you say you can get
Buddhas because they come from the
Dharma and the sa who's talking the
other guy
then we should say by the way the the
answer to a statement of consequence is
I never said there's no Dharma I never
said there's no ST what are you talking
about and he says yes it is you did say
that you said they were
empty you said the teachings were empty
you said the people practicing the
teachings are empty therefore there can
be no Buddhist created by those two guys
because they're empty empty means they
don't exist and we're like
oi in the diamond business there uh
Diamond business is all Jewish
everybody's like o o you're so stupid
you know uh that's that's not how you
make a Buddha okay that's not what we
mean when we say empty we don't mean
they don't exist we just mean they don't
exist without my seats that's all we
never said there's no Dharma we never
said there's no
sa you know we never said that if we did
say that maybe you're right okay but
you're not right the other guy's never
right by the way suang knows
this okay now uh I'll say the second
half of the verse you tell me who's
talking okay who's talking if you talk
about emptiness the way you're talking
about emptiness it hurts the whole idea
of the three
jeels
I don't know it could be Nar could be
the other guy don't forget the other guy
is saying if you if Nar if you keep
insisting that everything is empty
you're gonna destroy the three
jewels okay cuz cuz you're destroying
the two that create the third okay
you're destroying the two that create
the third therefore there could be no
jeel there could be no three jewels when
I had this
breakthrough in the G course and they
taught me what's really the three jewels
I was like wow you know I was like Wow
because every one of the three jewels is
emptiness and I was like it just blew me
away you know I'm not supposed to go
Buddha Diamond S please help me you
know I'm not supposed to say that I'm
I'm supposed to say Buddha is emptiness
Dharma is emptiness sa is emptiness
thank you very much you know stuff like
that you know that's worship that's
religion in Buddhism it's not go to the
temple and and make prostrations and
things like that it's not stup us okay
it's not that's not
Buddhism uh Buddhism is Buddhism is
emptiness in three packages Buddhism is
emptiness in three packages later you
you can quote me okay you should put
that in the book of gishi
Michaels uh Buddha is emptiness in three
different packages now I'll give a
hundred bucks if uh somebody can tell me
why and by the way this is a test to see
if you passed ACI course number
two uh if you can tell
me why is the three jewels all connected
with emptiness and in is going to take a
shot talk loud okay and slow don't
forget you're you're being
translated uh we do not talk here about
the Buddha the Dharma and the Sana we
talk here about the Jewel of the Buddha
The Jewel of the Dharma and the Jewel of
the Sanaa The Jewel of the Buddha is
emptiness of the dharmakaya his W
excellent emptiness of the Buddha wait
say it again the Jewel of the Buddha the
Jewel of the Buddha is the emptiness of
the Buddha is the emptiness of the
Buddha and the this is the only thing
that is common between us and
them okay so it's actually we are
feasible it's visibility we can become
Buddhas uh second is the Jewel of the
Dharma is
the actually uh the realizations uh that
we get on the past uh meaning see
emptiness directly yeah reaching Nana
and Buddah Hood anything else whoa hot
um so it is actually the fact that uh we
can reach something on the path there is
a path uh and the Jewel of the S is the
realizations in the minds of the
community Aras and realized beings so um
it actually from the other side it
confirms that the teachings do work so I
would say that's a $300 answer
to
[Applause]
yeah and and you got to get used to it
okay uh we don't build a
stoer so you can go pray to it or
something like that we we're not praying
to a piece of rock you know uh no and
you have to be careful with stupas you
have to be careful with stupas okay you
are not worshiping a stoa there's lots
of mountains here they're much bigger
cheaper uh you can pray to them if you
want okay uh so when you pray to Buddha
uh you're actually praying to The
Emptiness of a Buddha
okay the Buddha nothing about the Buddha
is coming from their own side when you
meet a Buddha they are coming
from you they're coming from you and if
you don't understand that you are
worshiping the Buddha the wrong way okay
and so I'd say in the history of
Buddhism there's probably very few
people who who were practicing
Buddhism okay there's very few people
who understood that okay I'm not bowing
down to some guy I'm bowing down to the
fact that he comes from
me okay that's very deep I was so happy
when I learned that you know Dharma then
is the understanding that he's coming
from me okay that's the teaching that's
the real teaching you you tend to think
of Dharma as books or
translations and it's not it's just to
understand the pen is Dharma people
understand the pen are taking refuge in
Dharma and only them only them and the
millions and millions of other Buddhists
don't know what the heck they're doing
okay they're they're not practicing
Buddhism okay uh and then
sa uh people who got it people who
understood
uh about the pen okay but and
classically they should have seen
emptiness directly but then Buddhism
becomes a very lonely thing so I think
we can say anyone who understands about
the pen maybe we should call ourselves
penist and not
Buddhists are you a penist yeah how you
that well from Pennsylvania your pen
your P okay uh anyway that's the big
teaching here okay and and
narina is like the seed for that idea
that came for the next 2,000 years after
him okay he triggered this he triggered
this understanding of
religion okay that's Buddhism and and to
bow down to a statue or to walk around a
stup it's not
Buddhism okay and unless you're thinking
about seeds while you're walking unless
you're thinking about seeds so hopefully
our stus will attract
penis and not Superstition the arrest is
superstition and and it leads to
disappointment
why they cannot help you they cannot
help you you can pray to Buddha all day
you won't make 10 cents you know they
they get when you pray to them they get
very cheap you know it doesn't work okay
and then you
get countless
people uh living their whole life in
doubt and disappointment and and it
applies to Christianity and and Buddhism
if you don't understand it you just
you're just GNA see your family die off
and you're G to see you know war and say
how can God allow this you know how can
this why is Buddha allow this killing
this morning in Gaza or Ukraine why why
you know otherwise you you're gonna give
it up you're G to give up so many people
millions of people give up religion
because they it doesn't make sense those
are the Smart Ones okay those are the
ones are they really they don't want to
believe Superstition and and they're
like this doesn't help anybody see what
I mean millions of people give it up
because they don't understand it they
don't understand this verse
okay pism okay let's get a copyright on
that right away okay uh okay next one
this is why we go so
slow yeah
5.49 Francisco uh this is a by the way
this is a book I wrote in threee Retreat
you probably know about it um
uh I was going to write a major
commentary to the yoga Sutra I got 800
Pages finished I sneaked it out of
retreat to my publisher in New York and
he sneaked me a letter back and said
it's too long thrown
out uh and then I wrote this book okay
and it's a short book about about the
yoga Su right and uh the essence of the
book one of the themes of the book is
that uh there's a young lady a thousand
years ago who actually became a gishi
secret secretly right and U and she gets
put into a prison wrongly she's She's
accused of stealing a book because in
those
days a woman shouldn't have a book
there's no reason because they're not
allowed to read
uh so anyway
uh and then the whole uh one of the
themes of the book is
that the inside of the prison becomes
the outside of the prison and it's only
the people in the prison who are
free and if you're not in the jail you
are in
jail okay if you're not in the jail
you're in jail she creates Freedom
inside jail and all the people who
didn't get to go to the jail are not
free they don't have freedom okay why
are we talking about
that why is gisha talking about that
does gisha have ADD does the guard I
just skipped from subject to subject you
know why am I talking about jails in the
prayers of good
name yeah it's one of his eight prayers
one of his eight prayers in the future
if somebody repeats my name seven times
uh at at least seven times probably
seven million times
uh they should never stay in a jail they
should never have to stand in jail so he
I like this prayer I really like this
prayer because you know we pray for poor
people we pray for sick
people but you know if you have done
work in a prison if you have taught in a
prison that's unbelievable suffering
there incredible suffering there okay
it's a special special suffering and
nobody thinks much about it because the
people there are bad people so we don't
care you know what what's one of the
saddest places in the whole world is
inside the
prison and and then people in their
heart they say that's okay they kill
somebody they should suffer or they
stole money they should suffer you know
uh like that I mean we
feel we don't feel compassion about
people in prison we feel like oh they
they put themselves there they should
stay there you know but uh we have a we
had a group uh here and we taught in the
prison near Tucson
and uh we taught for many years I think
we taught for 15 years there and uh it's
quite an experience you need a special
training the government uh train you to
go into the
prison and then you need a lot of
security
clearances and there's many many rules
to teach in the prison to go into the
prison to teach is there's many rules so
we did it we we got all the permission
we we had uh all these training to go
into why the training uh just before our
program there was another program by
actually by a Christian lady and the
Prisoner the handsome prisoner convince
her that he's he didn't do a crime and
she should help him to escape so she's
teaching in the
prison and and he's very handsome and I
think she fell in love with him and she
believed his story and the story is
always the same in the prison I you know
I was just standing there the police
grabbed me I didn't do anything you know
and uh it's always the same story
sometimes it's true most of the time
it's not true okay and she believed it
then she brought him some clothes they
tried to escape together the the prison
people are not
stupid and she went to prison okay
anyway
uh it's very difficult to teach in the
prison extremely difficult it's very
uncomfortable uh the prisoners are
angry uh they're they're violent uh they
work out all day they're strong and you
know they could one day they told us uh
you're supposed to come next Tuesday
right we're like yeah and they said
don't come
you know we're like what and they said
do not come next Tuesday stay home you
and we're like thanks and you know the
next Tuesday they had a riot and the
prisoners took over the jail you know
and uh it happens like that they plan it
like six weeks ahead or something and uh
so it's dangerous it's it's a dangerous
place to be
but and it it for us the reason we don't
do it anymore is when we all move to
Sedona it's a it's a 4H hour drive one
way it's eight hours driving to go teach
in the prison and we just couldn't do it
we just couldn't keep it up
so but I say one thing when you come out
of the prison from teaching
prisoners and you smell the fresh air on
the other side of the
fence you feel so happy when you teach
pris ERS you feel extreme joy you know
uh when you after you do it and you know
you get out of the jail they have to go
through three gates three guys check you
and then you go out and you're like ah
I'm glad I don't live in there and then
you're like I'm so glad I'm doing this
you know I'm so glad I'm helping
prisoners and so if you have a chance uh
it's a great great thing to do okay in
your own own
country uh it's e it's pretty easy to to
to make a course it's pretty easy to get
into the prison make sure you can get
out and
uh and it's extremely happy feeling to
help them because prisoners are the most
unhappy people in the world they are the
most unhappy people in the world there's
something very very
bad feeling when your Society tells you
we hate you and we don't want to see you
you see what I mean it's like 10 million
people are telling you I hate you I
don't care if I never see you again I'm
going to put you in a in a in a room and
I don't want to see you and I'm going to
forget about you in English they say I'm
going to throw away the key you know and
it's such a terrible feeling to war is
very similar war is very very
similar what is trauma in war War what
is trauma it means somebody wants you
gone from this Earth somebody wants to
take your life someone wants to kill you
someone hates you so much they want you
to disappear from this world and and
when you have that feeling for the first
time you know you really are a soldier
and and somebody tries to kill you and
you're
like there's one person in this world
who hates me so much they want me to
disappear from this world forever and
that that's what creates trauma in a war
someone wants me not to exist in this
world and it's a it's the worst feeling
it's the most terrible feeling someone
doesn't want me to exist someone wants a
world without me you know someone will
prefer a world without me that's what
trauma comes in a war is when you
finally someone shoots at you I had
someone shoot at me once and and then
you're you're like wow somebody doesn't
want me to exist in this world and the
feeling is is a the worst feeling you
know in prison is very very similar
someone doesn't want to see me for 20
years or 30 years they want me to
disappear from this world for for 20
years it's a terrible terrible
terrible psychologically it's a terrible
feeling all the guys in the prison have
this feeling you know everyone hates me
they don't even want to see me for 20
years it's a terrible terrible uh
suffering so uh this this medicine
Buddha good name I really like it that
he's praying for people in prison I I
love it it means he's he really
understands suffering he it's one of the
greatest sufferings in life when someone
says I would like to not see you for 20
years or or I would like to kill you
it's a terrible terrible suffering so I
think this uh prayer I love this prayer
okay we're going to look at the prayer
you ready
Francisco there's the prayer fifth
prayer there are those of us and other
loving living beings as well who are
kept in Chains and beaten and thrown
into prison and whose bodies are hurt by
people with all kinds of different
weapons until the day of their final
Enlightenment may all of us be
completely free
of ever being chained or beaten or
anything of the like May every sort of
bodily abuse come to a complete end in
this world that's uh his fifth prayer
okay uh that's the fifth prayer of good
me and I just want to say it's
a I I think it's a a good prayer to
focus on when you're doing medicine
Buddha practice I don't know there's so
many prayers dozens of prayers right
this particular prayer is very attract
RVE to me I I love this prayer because
that's
a to be put into prison is a is a
special suffering it's a special
suffering I went to prison
briefly uh I I was
uh protesting against the vi against the
Vietnam War and I got put into prison
and um it's very it's a great suffering
okay so anyway it's a great uh it's a
great prayer I think to me okay later
the Government contact me and said we
made a mistake I'm like
thanks they said we will remove your
record I said no I'm proud of it you can
keep it I'm keeping it so I still have
it right they tried to take they tried
to erase it I said no I'm proud it's my
good karma I want to keep it all right
uh 551
Francisco
um Lord Buddha says if you want to help
people in prison use the two
realities okay uh if you want to help
people in
prison use the two realities so we're
moving on to the two realities there's
two different realities and we're going
to talk about it
okay uh and this is a very very deep
subject uh whose book it came up in
somebody's book it's coming up this week
I think it's coming up in Mick's book I
think no
it's deceptive reality and Ultimate
Reality okay so Buddhism
teaches that reality divides into two
realities okay it's called K Demba and
dund deba okay KOB deba
means fake
reality and dundum d means real reality
okay uh Ultimate Reality okay so
Buddhism divides your world into two
kinds fake
reality and and real reality
okay you want to go deeper yeah fake
reality has two
parts okay you ready correct fake
reality and wrong fake
reality okay so we're going to go there
okay so let's say
again and by the way this is not
philosophical
BS I didn't say the real word
okay uh this is not just some philosophy
okay there's
no philosophy in the translation classes
for example that you cannot use in your
real life there's nothing there I it's a
joke at the end of the class is there
anything here you could use in your real
life it's a joke because it is the only
thing you could use in your real life
the rest is uh
BS okay everything else you learn in in
the University or something that's the
BS this is not the BS okay everything
you learn in the translation classes is
the only thing that can help you forget
those other courses okay all right uh
but anyway I don't say that publicly uh
so there's two I call it two and a half
realities okay uh and this is a deep
subject I'll go for five minutes then
we'll take
Q&A right Tim am I right or I go for
another 20 minutes how's it work
15 okay so we'll do Q&A in about five
minutes okay and if I don't finish this
topic we'll finish it in the next class
okay is that good Timothy okay uh
should I make a bet I don't know I mean
my money is getting stretched I should
stop
right see see there it
is let's take a that
uh so there's uh Ultimate Reality which
is emptiness okay Ultimate Reality and
and then there's deceptive reality and
it's interesting it's real both of them
are real okay both of them exist both of
them are real okay one is what it
seems and the other is not what it seems
okay but they're both real and they're
both valid okay there's two realities
one is Ultimate Reality and the other is
like relatively reality it's it's real
but it's not what it looks like okay uh
anything that well that's
tricky Ultimate Reality is a double
negative what's that
mean there's nothing that don't come
from seeds yeah okay that's Ultimate
Reality okay there's
nothing that doesn't come from seeds
that's Ultimate Reality okay you you
know everybody says I want to see
emptiness I want to see emptiness it's
very simple there's nothing that don't
come from sin okay that that's bad
English but it's funny okay there's
there ain't there ain't nothing that
don't come from sin there's nothing that
doesn't come from SE that's emptiness
very
simple gu how am I going to use that how
am I going to use that how do I use that
in my real life come on it's the only
thing you can use in your real life okay
because what it means is every
irritating person you ever met was a
mirror of you and not a partly a mirror
100% mirror not only every irritating
person you ever met every you
ever met was coming from you okay not
that that doesn't say it well enough
every you ever met is a perfect
reflection of
okay every detail about them is you okay
every little detail how they hurt you is
coming from you it's not that generally
they're coming from you or something
like that that's not true every single
detail the way they talk the way they
criticize you the time they criticize
you the way they everything is every
detail coming exact reflection of you
okay uh and and there's nothing nothing
else in the world that's emptiness so
don't tell me Emptiness is hard to see
okay the world is full of irritating
people
okay they were sent to remind you about
emptiness okay they are the Dharma right
so there was a famous joke here we had a
visitor from I don't know where and uh
they I think they wanted to be a
volunteer here or something like that
and uh they were having a rough time and
uh it's a hard place to be by the way
these guys the people you see who work
here uh help out here it's extremely
hard place to be
karmically it's intense Karma to be here
you you got to be a real special person
to survive here karmically it's because
the karma is so heavy the karma is so
high then so anyway this person was
trying to be a volunteer and and we had
a class they were in the kitchen or
something and uh and we had a class and
we were talking about this subject that
emptiness means there's nothing that
doesn't come from you to put it
dependent origination way to put it the
opposite way everything you see is a
reflection of you The Emptiness way
nothing you see is not coming from you
the dependent origination way everything
you see is coming from you okay that's
dependent or that's the
relationship so anyway uh they uh we
finished the class we talked about how
everything's coming from you every
irritating person you ever met is
directly coming from you you know and
then this lady came in and she was talk
we were all sitting around and and she
was she said God this diamond mountain
place she and we're like what and she
says I'm surrounded by idiots you know
and we're all
like and we were
like yeah you're
right completely
right all right any Q&A let's do Q&A by
the way why we have these two books here
uh we'll come back to it in the next
class okay there's a special message
here maybe you
remember it was a long time ago like two
days
ago whose class was
that Allison's class yeah okay all right
Q&A maybe online Tim you got any
interesting I have a Q&A I donated
coffee for this
program and this is not
it
I think there's some corruption in
selling the good coffee
and just
kidding rob you can go
first uh hello can you hear me um
related to that what you were just
saying about the person who's you know
I'm surrounded by idiots and so sort of
when you're in a throws of that when
you're sort of having this understanding
that you that if you are surrounded by
idiots and you feel like that's coming
you are it's coming from you how do you
deal with that sort of in that time when
you feel like it's all on you and
there's like this pressure of like oh my
god I've created every idiot in the
world so how do I in a practical way
deal with that yeah good basically and
kind of deploy it to your life yeah I
think what Rob's saying is and it
happens to me every
day uh if I'm thinking of why did
somebody say something mean to me or why
did somebody do something mean to
me I don't know why I the people think I
have the nicest cabin I
don't uh it's a good
cabin but you got to walk to the ouse no
matter how cold the weather is and then
you got to sit you got to put your
bottom on a cold
scene like in the winter that one moment
is true suffering
uh so anyway so I won't walk and I don't
know why but I remember my Buddhism out
there I don't know why you know so
somebody's giving me a hard time and I'm
grumpy all the way to the ouse you know
I'm like grumpy I'm
like and then when I get that
shock uh of the cold toilet
scene suddenly my mind
clears you know and I'm like they're
coming from me you know and I'm like
they're coming from me you know and what
Rob's saying is I mean that can be a
very important time of the
day uh it's always an important time of
the day even if you don't have a cold
seat but uh but the question is um what
do you do with that because
then then you feel really bad you know
Ukraine problem coming from me Israel
problem coming from me it's overwhelming
you know all these mean people coming
from me you know it's like too much like
how do you what do you do with that how
do you handle that how can you sustain
that
thought for more than a few minutes
because it's painful it's really really
painful and and I would I agree you know
for for the first few seconds until it
warms
up I feel clear you know maybe it's the
cold but I'm clear like I'm like okay
this person who complained to me they
come from me I understand that and it
makes my life easier for for a minute it
makes my life easier I say okay so I can
fix things you know and mainly I cannot
blame them and and that freedom
from blaming other people is so
refreshing it's so nice you know like
okay I can let go
of disliking this person because it's
coming from me I can let go of that you
know there's a Moment of clarity on the
cold
seat and then uh it gets overwhelming it
feels like God that means every mean
person in the world is coming from me
all these murderers all these people who
bombing people they all coming from me
it's too much it just feels like too
much you know so I think what Rob's
saying is uh how do you deal with that
you know how do you deal with that and I
think uh in my
case I I try not to go there I I don't
uh I back off I I don't at that moment I
don't try to take responsibility for
three million it's too much you
know I just I back off and I say okay
don't go there is every bad person in
this world coming from you yes how does
it feel I feel really bad well why don't
we just stick to the one person you know
let's just work on the one person so I
think for Buddhist
practice don't try to solve the whole
world at one time it's too much you just
going to go crazy you know it's too much
deal with the one person who irritates
you and work on them okay and then the
rest just be like I'll take care of you
the rest of your later I I'm
focusing on one today you know and just
uh focus on that one person and I think
it's a practical way the second one is
much easier the third one is almost
effortless you see what I mean so start
with one and and don't tell
Veronica I use the word okay and uh and
then slowly uh you it's easier if you
start with one and then do the rest but
if you if you feel guilty for all the
bad people in the world you're just
going to collapse you're just going to
feel depressed
okay you also required don't forget
you're required to do coffee meditation
you know you also created every
beautiful person in the world and if you
don't take credit for that and if you
don't give equal time to thinking about
that you are failed your Buddhism it's
it's not Buddhism anymore then it's just
self punishment you know what I mean
okay so you're the
contract with Lord Buddha is equal time
you know did you create all the
in the world yes did you create all the
beautiful people in the world yes okay
you got to give it equal time right
otherwise you're not practicing and it's
very hard okay
question okay if I will start with one
like me yes with
myself I understand that it's me and I
will start with from me and I will um
understand that I I did a lot of stuff
let's say like dangerous stuff it's
don't paying taxes you like about
confession you don't go to IRS yes you
you do something else you know like like
I mean like guiltiness it's caused
confession correct so you have to
confess your sins yeah and you like okay
I don't pay in tax taxes I'm not going
to IRS and tell them this because it's
dangerous things but uh okay forget
about this I can do some Charities
whatever I can like things think how I
can return my taxes different way but
what if I all the time feel guilty about
being the mother in the world and raise
my kids not right because I have to tell
you when you are a parent number one
what you have for all entire life
guiltiness about you did a lot of
mistakes since day once it's like minute
your child was born and I have five kids
and I always struggling because I have
one child it's my stepdaughter I took my
husband he was a single father and I
delivered four kids we always hate each
other with my oldest one because she was
the only child for her father and I
actually married him and we still hate
each other and we
cannot kind of go through it my four
kids every day I see a lot of mistakes
and I always sit and crying hours in my
car and ask how I can fix it I cannot I
cannot it's done it's gone they eat fast
they play Roblox at 11:00 p.m. and I
hate this you know they don't go to
shower and brushing their teeth and run
to the school with no brushing teeth and
I text them did you brush your teeth Mom
I'm sorry I was late to my boss and you
know actually it's kind of like really
this guiltiness it goes to confession
okay I confess but what have to how can
I fix it okay
uh here's a basic thing okay here's the
thing to remember the best uh teachings
are the short ones
right
uh the kid didn't brush their teeth and
they went to the
school uh how did they go to the school
they have things attached to their body
called
legs okay they have legs all
right why they have
legs why do they have legs you gave them
the legs okay you gave them the legs
every we were talking about it in the
parenting class I I believe I believe
the number is correct the average
expense of a kid in this state which is
one of the poorest states is $330,000 a
year the average income in this uh
State not where I live my where I live
is 25% below that
but uh it's $30,000 I'll say it again
the average expense of a to have a child
in this state is $30,000 a year the
average income in the state of Arizona
is $30,000 a
year it's impossible to be a parent to
be a mom to be a dad in this
state
mathematically it's impossible you know
you you are suffering it's very very
very difficult to you can say my kid
didn't brush my teeth or their teeth but
who put the clothes on them why they
have a body you fed them you know you
how can you worry about their teeth you
gave them teeth you know I me okay and
if you don't give equal
time to thinking about you gave them the
teeth uh uh you paid for the toothbrush
they are sleeping in your house because
you paid for the house and you are
working really
hard uh and it's a 20year contract
minimum okay my uh I have a friend she's
69 now their mom's still paying for her
stuff okay so I mean 20 years if you're
lucky 69 years if you're not lucky you
know and how can you say you're a bad
mother how can you say that they the
body they have exists because of your
sweat and and your hard work and you
struggling to make some money and and
they're alive and they have a body and
okay they go to the school with dir
teeth but they got teeth and uh they got
a school and they got a house to go from
to go to the school and uh so I think uh
you're being Prejudice you're being
Prejudice you know that's like I don't
like this person his color is wrong skin
color is wrong you are prejudice against
yourself you're a Prejudice to yourself
you're thinking about the 1% that
brushing the teeth and you're not
thinking about the 99% of the teeth you
know so they exist they have a body
because of you and you gave them the
first seed of their body and and you
risk your life to have a
child I I I think you are
prejudice against yourself
okay all right equal
rights okay equal rights